<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, at St. Mary le Bow, on Nov. 5, 1683 being the commemoration-day of our deliverance from a popish conspiracy / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53969</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1095</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1882</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12576508</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12576508</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63594</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53969)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63594)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 328:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, at St. Mary le Bow, on Nov. 5, 1683 being the commemoration-day of our deliverance from a popish conspiracy / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Will. Abington ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63594:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63594:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Lord Mayor AND COURT of ALDERMEN, At St. <hi>Mary le Bow,</hi> on <hi>Nov.</hi> 5. 1683.</p>
            <p>BEING THE Commemoration-Day Of our Deliverance from a <hi>Popiſh Conſpiracy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Edward Pelling,</hi> Chaplain to His Grace the Duke of <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Abington</hi> next the <hi>Wonder</hi> Tavern in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63594:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63594:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable Sir <hi>Henry Tulce,</hi> Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and to the Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Court of Aldermen.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen your Lordſhip and your Brethren were pleaſed to pitch upon me for your Preacher on the late Solemn Occaſion, I had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to conclude, that knowing my Principles and Way, you might expect from me a Diſcourſe like unto the Author, Blunt and Plain, and (as I hope your Lordſhip doth believe) Loyal and Honeſt.</p>
            <p>And truly had I had no other Tye upon me but Good Manners, that was enough to oblige me not to defraud your Lordſhip wholly of your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations. But I have this to ſay more, that by my Experience I have found, that the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of plain Truths after a plain manner (however ſome may call it Intemperate Zeal) is in this Age the moſt Effectual way of Inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:63594:3"/>
People, eſpecially the ordinary ſort of Men, who are moſt apt to run away with miſtakes, and who need the moſt of our Care and Inſtructions, becauſe they are the Hands and Tools which Politick Male-contents imploy to Diſturb the Peace and Eſtabliſht Government.</p>
            <p>I had therefore a particular regard to the neceſſities of theſe, eſpecially in the Practical part of this Diſcourſe; which I thought neceſſary to adapt to our preſent Circumſtances, as a more profitable courſe than either to enter into Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, or to tell a Story of the <hi>Fifth</hi> of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord, I did hope that your Lordſhip and the Court would have gratified my Deſires by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing me from Publiſhing theſe Papers to an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable and Cenſorious World. But ſince you have been pleaſed to determine it otherwiſe, I Submit to your Pleaſure, being ever ready to pay all due Obedience to my Governours, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to your Lordſhip, whoſe Endeavours for the Good of the Government in Church and State, I beſeech God to bleſs with Succeſſes ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to your Zeal for both. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Bounden, and Obedient Servant, Edw. Pelling.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63594:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Luke XIX. 42.</bibl>
               <q>If thou hadſt known, even Thou, at leaſt in this Thy day, the things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto thy Peace!</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Fore-caſting of Events, and the Prudent Providing againſt the <hi>Worſt,</hi> as it is a Neceſſary Courſe for us all to take in the Management of our <hi>Private</hi> and <hi>Particular</hi> Concernments, ſo 'tis a moſt Uſeful Courſe in the Governmet of <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>National</hi> Affairs, eſpecially in Lowring Weather and Threatning Times, when a Nation ſeems to be brought under an abſolute Neceſſity, either of being Wiſe in Time, or of being undone for ever.</p>
            <p>'Tis plain that this was the Caſe of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> when our Saviour Lamented over her, and was a Mourner at her Funerals before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand: her Days were numbred out unto her; her laſt Hours were ſpending apace, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63594:4"/>
She was limited to a certain Time, which the purpoſe of a Patient and Juſt God had fixt her: ſo that one of theſe two things She was bound to Reſolve upon, either to bethink her ſelf of her Follies, while the Sands were yet in her Glaſs, or to Periſh and be Deſtroyed without any Remedy or Controul.</p>
            <p>That Merciful Jeſus who came into the World, not to Deſtroy Mens Lives, but to Save them, and to Retrieve and Succour that which was Loſt, not only told her her ſad Doom, if She perſiſted ſtill in her wonted courſe of Obſtinacy and Rebellion (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo many Meroies God had ſhewed her, and ſo many Deliverances he had wrought for her) but moreover he Courted her with the moſt Paſſionate Expreſſions of Tenderneſs and Goodneſs, that now, at the laſt, after that the Patience of God had waited for her <hi>ſo long,</hi> ſhe would be True to her own Intereſt, and be Merciful to her ſelf: for the Particle (<hi>If</hi>) is an <hi>Optative</hi> in this place, a note of <hi>Deſire</hi> and Earneſt <hi>Longing;</hi> as if our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour had ſaid, <hi>O that thou hadſt known; would to God thou wouldſt conſider and do the things which belong unto thy Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words I have choſen to Diſcourſe of now, becauſe they contain that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63594:4"/>
which every Provident Nation ſhould make of the Divine Goodneſs; and eſpceially we of <hi>This Nation,</hi> who have had ſuch Ample and Wonderful Experience of the Mercies of God (and particularly in that Signal and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Inſtance of it, which we Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate this Day) that one would think, <hi>Louder</hi> warnings could not well be given to <hi>Any</hi> Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under Heaven, than what hath been given to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, To know the things which belong unto our Peace.</hi> For though <hi>One</hi> end of our Meeting be to Praiſe and Bleſs the Keeper of our <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> for this Days Aſtoniſhing Deliverance of our King, of the whole Family Royal, of the Three Eſtates of the Realm, and of our whole Church and Nation, from the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Deſigns of our old good Friends at <hi>Rome,</hi> with whom <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Villany</hi> is <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious;</hi> yet this is not the <hi>whole,</hi> nor indeed the <hi>greateſt</hi> part of our Buſineſs. For, Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of Deſtruction are Indications and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of mens <hi>Demerits;</hi> and a Scourge, though it be not <hi>Felt,</hi> yet is a Monitor from Heaven that tells us what we <hi>ſhall</hi> feel in the end, if we be not Tractable; and if in <hi>Time</hi> we be not Diſciplin'd into that Wiſdom which is Peaceable and Pure. So that every Deliverance being but a <hi>Summoning</hi> of us to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63594:5"/>
our Duty, we are not only to look <hi>Backward</hi> upon it, nor barely to Read it as a Story of Gods Providence; but we are chiefly to look <hi>Forward,</hi> to the thing that it <hi>Points</hi> at, to the Amendment of our Lives, and to the Practice of the things which belong unto our Peace, while it is yet <hi>Our</hi> day.</p>
            <p>Ingratitude, though it be the <hi>Baſeſt</hi> and moſt <hi>Odious</hi> Sin, yet 'tis the <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical</hi> Guilt of <hi>this</hi> Nation; that, when no People under Heaven are ſo deeply Indebted to Gods Providence as <hi>We</hi> are, Men neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſuffer, if not the <hi>Memory,</hi> vet the <hi>Senſe</hi> of his Goodneſs to ſlide ſo eaſily away from them, as if they had nothing to do, but ſtill to be trying Concluſions with Heaven, and to make freſh Experiments of Gods Mercy, how <hi>Long,</hi> and how <hi>Far</hi> 'tis Poſſible for it to <hi>Laſt.</hi> What have we learnt from this <hi>Days</hi> Mercy, but to fling Invectives at the Papiſts (though, I confeſs, the <hi>greateſt</hi> Invectives can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>too much?</hi>) what other uſe have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny made of the King's <hi>Reſtauration,</hi> but <hi>This</hi> onely, to try whether they could Rout him again out of his Kingdome, or diſpatch him quite out of the World? Nay (if I may have Liberty to ask it) what have they learnt from the Dangers of a late <hi>Popiſh</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63594:5"/>
Plot, but to Form a <hi>Fanatick</hi> Conſpiracy, and to Mock God Solemnly by Studying Treaſon Themſelves after a Day of Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation for the very ſame Horrid Sin in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? I cannot tell what Uſe we ſhall make of the Late<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Deliverance of the King and the whole Kingdome, which God hath wrought for us but <hi>Yeſterday,</hi> as it were: but I am greatly afraid, that the Senſe even of <hi>This</hi> Deliverance will not ſtick by us long neither; eſpecially ſince ſome begin already to look upon that as a <hi>Sham,</hi> which was one of the greateſt Miracles of Mercy, that ever we or our Fore-Fathers have ſeen.</p>
            <p>Lord! after this Rate what ſhall we do, and what will become of us in the End? Little do Men conſider, that theſe Reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of us from Perdition, are intended on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to lengthen our Time for <hi>Repentance;</hi> and 'tis a general Fault among us, that while we are ſtriving, who ſhall be too hard for the other, we do not look up unto Heaven, where the Righteous God is weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Mercies</hi> and our <hi>Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Stir Men up therefore to a, <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>Timely</hi> Care of a Matter which is of ſuch vaſt Importance and Concernment to our whole Nation, I have pitch't upon theſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63594:6"/>
Words of our Saviour, which with weeping Eyes he uſed concerning <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in the like Caſe. And before I take upon more to ſpeak of the things which belong unto our Peace, as Affairs ſtand with us in this Juncture; there are Two Points couched in my Text, which I beg leave to offer to your Serious Conſideration.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt, that the moſt Profligate Nation have Overtures of Happineſs, a <hi>Day</hi> of Peace given them; ſo that if they be Undone, the fault is their own, and their Deſtruction is of themſelves.</p>
            <p>There hardly ever was a more Wicked and Profligate People in the World (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that <hi>Profeſt Religion</hi> and the Knowledg of the True God) than that People was, which now was within the Walls of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> an Ungrateful and Rebellious Generation: Men that were Addicted to Hypocryſie, to Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, to Cruelty, and to all manner of Wickedneſs, <hi>Idolatry</hi> only <hi>excepted.</hi> Men that Rejected the Prince of Peace, that Reſiſted the Holy Ghoſt, that ſhut their Eyes againſt the Truth, and obſtinately oppoſed it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the moſt Convincing Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which were given on its ſide, even
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63594:6"/>
by Miracles from Heaven. Men that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook their own Mercies, and were ſo Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſet againſt Him, that brought thoſe Mercies in his hands, that they only ſtudyed how they might now Treat themſelves with his Blood at the Paſſover. Never did any Nation take a more direct Courſe to bring themſelves to Ruin, than the <hi>Jews</hi> took at this time: and yet they had their <hi>Day,</hi> an Opportunity given them to ſave themſelves from Deſtruction, if they would have been Wiſe in <hi>Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was that <hi>Time of Viſitation</hi> which we find mentioned at verſ. 44. of this Chapter. For there is <hi>Viſitatio Miſericordiae</hi> as well as <hi>Juſtitiae,</hi> a time when Men are Viſited in a way of <hi>Mercy,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> were Viſited at their Deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and as we of this Nation have been often Viſited with many ſtupendious Deliverances from the moſt imminent Dangers all along from the Beginning of the Reformation unto this day. And thus Chriſt Viſited <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> when he Rode unto her in Tryumph (the only Triumphal Progreſs which he took in his whole Life) he went to her to <hi>Heal,</hi> and to <hi>Save,</hi> and to <hi>Deliver</hi> her from Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This <hi>Lucid Interval</hi> and <hi>Lightning</hi> of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63594:7"/>
Mercy before her Tragical overthrow, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Day of Jeruſalem, Her</hi> Day, as it was diſtinguiſh't from <hi>Gods</hi> Day, that time of <hi>Judgment</hi> which followed afterwards. Our Saviour himſelf did thus diſtinguiſh between theſe two times: for ſpeaking of that Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which was coming, how <hi>the Jews ſhould be led away Captive into all Nations, and Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem ſhould be Troden down of the Gentiles, Theſe</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>are the Days of Vengeance,</hi> Lu. 21. 22. It was a far <hi>different</hi> Time from that which he called here a Time of <hi>Viſitation:</hi> This was a Time of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Mercy:</hi> now he went to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with Peace and Pardon in his Hand, if ſhe would not bid him defiance. As yet the <hi>Jews</hi> were not utterly loſt, but they might have been happy if they had not been wanting to themſelves; becauſe in the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt them God had reſerved to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Power of <hi>Revocation:</hi> his purpoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them, was not <hi>Peremptory</hi> as yet: for though Ruin and Exciſion had been, time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time, denounced againſt them, yet the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces were not <hi>Abſolute;</hi> but as his Promiſes to them were on Condition of their <hi>Obedience,</hi> ſo all his Threatnings againſt them, were on Condition of their <hi>Impenitence,</hi> if they Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to do the things which did belong unto their Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:63594:7"/>And the Reaſon of this is grounded upon that Infinite <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and moſt Tender <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion,</hi> which is an <hi>Inſeparable</hi> Property of the Divine Nature. His Mercy is over all his Works; and his Providence is watchful over Mens very <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes</hi> to keep them from being loſt, and many times too when Men are upon the very <hi>Brink</hi> of the Pit, and in the greateſt <hi>Extremity</hi> of Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as his Providence Kept and Sav'd This <hi>Our</hi> Church and Nation, even when the <hi>Powder</hi> and the <hi>Touch-wood</hi> was now <hi>ready,</hi> and but a few Hours before the Intended Blow: <hi>God doth not willingly Afflict nor Grieve the Children of Men;</hi> and when he threatneth to do it, it is with an Intent to prevent the doing of it, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Correcting and Humbling People by the Fears of the Rod. Judgment comes heavily from him, and with a Holy kind of Reluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy and Regret; and ſo it is called his ſtrange Work, and his ſtrange Act, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Interpreters Underſtand that Place in <hi>Iſ.</hi> 28. 21.</p>
            <p>This Conſideration is of very great Uſe to us, to make us <hi>Steddy, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright</hi> and <hi>Couragious</hi> even in Times that are full of Difficulties and Horrous. The Bowels of God are ever Yern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing toward us; and if we do not Miſ-imploy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63594:8"/>
or ſquander away thoſe Bleſſed Oportunities which he gives us, we need not doubt, but his Providence will Protect and Preſerve us, though the World be never ſo Impatient and Mad, and on which Hand ſoever it be that Danger threatneth us, whether it be from the <hi>Popiſh,</hi> or from the <hi>Proteſtant Jeſuit.</hi> But yet (that we may not preſume too much, or be <hi>Conſident</hi> if we be <hi>Careleſs</hi>) we muſt note, that though Vengance be called a <hi>Strange</hi> work, yet 'tis <hi>Gods</hi> work nevertheleſs, when he is forced to it, and when all other Courſes are <hi>ineffectual.</hi> Mercy hath the <hi>firſt</hi> turn, but Juſtice takes the <hi>ſecond,</hi> when the <hi>forbearance and Goodneſs of God do not lead Men to Repentance.</hi> Go we to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: She had her <hi>Day</hi> indeed, wherein ſhe might have known the things which did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto her Peace: but by the Tenor of our Saviours Mournful Speech ſhe might Collect, that ſhe ſhould be Irrecoverably Loſt and Undone, if ſhe <hi>ſlept</hi> or <hi>ſported</hi> her <hi>time away. O that thou hadſt known, even thou at leaſt in this thy day!</hi> intimating that <hi>Another</hi> day was at hand, and that <hi>Gods</hi> day would come next, and that a time of <hi>Vengeance</hi> would certainly follow the time of her <hi>Viſitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:63594:8"/>2. Whence I proceed to the Second Point, That when a Froward and Stubborn Nation do Obſtinately refuſe to do the things which belong unto their Peace, they fall at laſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an ineluctable Fate, and Ruin themſelves by an inevitable kind of Nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſity, when <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is Ripe, and <hi>Men</hi> are Ripe for it, then the Purpoſe of God concerning the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a City or a Kingdom in general, is a <hi>Definite, Peremptory</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nalterable</hi> Purpoſe; ſo that when Gods Time of Striking is fully come, there is no poſſible way to evade, or ward off the Blow: This is clear from Gods dealing with thoſe People over whom our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Wept now. Though they had a Day, and a <hi>long</hi> Day too, yet their Light utterly <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh't</hi> at the laſt; ſo that when <hi>Titus</hi> came with his Army againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> all her Time of <hi>Grace</hi> was <hi>ſpent,</hi> and her Hour of <hi>Darkneſs</hi> and <hi>Deſolation</hi> began. God would not then be intreated for the Hardened <hi>Jews,</hi> nor was it poſſible by any means to Reverſe the Decree that was gone out againſt them. <hi>Joſephus</hi> the Hiſtorian was at that time in the City; and when he ſaw the Blockade about it, and how impoſſible it was for the City to Eſcape, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the various Methods, and the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63594:9"/>
Reſtleſs endeavours which the fooliſh <hi>Jews</hi> uſed, he was plainly, ſenſible that they fought againſt God, and ſtrove againſt his <hi>Irreſiſtible</hi> Will; and therefore would have perſwaded them to Reſolutions of <hi>Surrendring,</hi> being fully convinced, that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> at that time was under the ſame unavoidable Neceſſity of being taken, as it had been under before, in the time of <hi>Nebuchaddonoſor</hi> and <hi>Antiochus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Scripture ſometimes ſpeaks of Mens <hi>filling up their Sins,</hi> and of their <hi>filling up the Meaſure of their Iniquities.</hi> For ſuch is the Mercy of God, that he doth not ſtrike upon <hi>every</hi> (though <hi>Juſt</hi>) provocation; but ſtays to ſoe how Far, and to what Degree Men will go on in their Impieties in ſpight of all Means and Calls to the contrary: and 'till the Cry of Mens Sins be Great and General, God is not wont to bring a Curſe upon a Nation ſo, as to Bury it in Ruin. Thus ſpeaking of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> how they were to be Extirpated, he pointed to the Time, when it was to be done, <hi>viz. in the Fourth Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> not till then; for (ſaid he) <hi>the Iniquity of the</hi> Amorites <hi>is not yet full,</hi> Gen. 15. 16. As King <hi>Solomon</hi> did ſet <hi>Shimei</hi> his Bounds, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that if he paſſed over the Brook <hi>Kidron,</hi> he ſhould ſurely dye, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2. 37. So does
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63594:9"/>
the great Governour of the World deal with Evil Men, eſpecially ſuch Men as <hi>Shimei</hi> was, <hi>Perſidious Wretches</hi> and <hi>Traytors;</hi> he gives them their Rope and <hi>Tedder,</hi> but of ſuch a <hi>length</hi> and <hi>ſcantling;</hi> and when they come to their <hi>Kidrons,</hi> the next ſtep they take is into Deſtruction. For God cannot but hate all manner of Wickedneſs, eſpecially when 'tis a <hi>Trade;</hi> and moſt of all when 'tis a <hi>Long</hi> and an <hi>Old</hi> Trade. This is enough to wear out the Patience, even of a Merciful God; and then Men muſt come to a full recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for a <hi>Long Indulgence,</hi> and ſo many <hi>Acts of Grace,</hi> which they have Abuſed.</p>
            <p>And would to God we ſhould lay this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration to Heart, and for the ſake of this Poor Nation, Tranſmit it into Practice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times; and not preſume too much upon the Divine Clemency, as if it would never be <hi>Night</hi> with us, what uſe ſoever we make of our Day of Peace! 'Tis true; as the Malice and Deſigns of our Enemies, ſo have the kindneſſes of our God, been to us, even from the Days <hi>of Old,</hi> and ever ſince the Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring from an high, began to Viſit us in the Morning of the <hi>Reformation.</hi> Thoſe Acts and Struglings under K. <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> could not keep the Truth of Religion from break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63594:10"/>
out. Thoſe Commotions in the Reign of K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, were not able to hinder the <hi>Perfecting</hi> of the Work which his Father had <hi>begun.</hi> Thoſe <hi>Victims</hi> which were off red in the <hi>Marian</hi> Perſecution, ſerved only to bring down, as it were, God upon the Earth to be with his Saints and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtyrs in the Flam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. In the Days of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> when in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the whole Papal World, at Home and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, formed their Deſigns, and put th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Arms againſt <hi>One Woman,</hi> God ſtood by this Church ſo, that no hidden Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, nor open Force, proved Effective of thoſe Ends which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> aimed at, with ſo much Confidence. The Treaſon of this Day, in the time of K. <hi>James,</hi> what did it do elſe, but <hi>Blow up</hi> the Intereſt of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Cauſe, and Kindle ſuch a Zeal againſt that <hi>Sanguinary</hi> Religion, as Burneth yet in our Breaſts, and we hope will be <hi>Warm</hi> in the Veins of our <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity</hi> to the Worlds End? Nay, to go on a little farther to the Reign of that Incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince, and in the End, Royal Martyr, K. <hi>Charls</hi> the Firſt; when a <hi>Domeſtick</hi> Enemy undertook the Quarrel of a <hi>Foreign</hi> one, and <hi>Votes,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> Roar'd Louder than <hi>Bulls;</hi> though a <hi>Cromwell</hi> was a more Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Devil than a <hi>Catesbie</hi> or a <hi>Garnet,</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63594:10"/>
the <hi>Conſiſtory</hi> was a more Miſchievous Legion than the <hi>Conclave;</hi> yet God was ſo Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to our Sins, that he ſuffered not this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ro be quite eaten up of the <hi>Vermine</hi> that it <hi>bred;</hi> but after a long <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Plague of <hi>Lice</hi> made us whole and Sound again, if happily we would be taught by that <hi>Severe</hi> Judgment, to <hi>Sin no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Great and Continual Deliverances 'tis neceſſary for me to mention, and for us <hi>All</hi> to be thankful for, that we may ſet forth the Honour of Gods Name, and the Glory of his Mercy, which from Age to Age he hath ſo abundantly ſhew'd to this our <hi>Sion,</hi> as if he had ſaid of <hi>it,</hi> as he did once of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Here will I dwell, for I have a Delight therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet, 'tis a moſt <hi>Impolitick</hi> and <hi>Dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> Courſe for us, to lean ſtill upon the Goodneſs of God, if we be not careful to Anſwer the great <hi>Ends</hi> of all his Longanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Compaſſion. For <hi>his Spirit mill not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be ſtriving with Men:</hi> there is a Time when he will give overall further Luctations with an Incorrigible People. And I Pray God <hi>we</hi> may not be made a <hi>fearful</hi> Inſtance to demonſtrate to the World the Truth of this. But if our Conſciences are not Seared, we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63594:11"/>
cannot but be Senſible how near our Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude hath lately brought us <hi>again</hi> to the <hi>Edge</hi> of the Praecipice, and to the very <hi>Margin</hi> of that Gulph, which would for ever hath Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed us all up, had not our God after a moſt Providential manner, opened our Eyes, and diſcovered unto us the <hi>Depths</hi> of Satan.</p>
            <p>Though our Nation hath for ſome time paſt been troubled, and Giddy with a <hi>Meagram,</hi> yet now we may have our Senſes at Command; we may clearly diſcern the <hi>Wolf</hi> under the <hi>Lamb-Skin;</hi> and if we be not willfully Blind, we have <hi>Light</hi> enough to diſcover thoſe who are <hi>Proteſtants</hi> by Profeſſion, but as very <hi>Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fians</hi> and <hi>Regicides</hi> by Principle, as the <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites.</hi> For the difference is not great, whether a <hi>Powder-Treaſon</hi> be Acted at the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memt</hi>-Houſe, or at <hi>Rumbolds:</hi> the <hi>Principle</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which both Parties Act, is the ſame; and it ſeems, the <hi>Reward</hi> was to have been <hi>alike</hi> too; and Statutes and Monuments were to have been ſet up in Honour of <hi>Thee,</hi> as <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> Picture was ſet up at <hi>Rome</hi> with this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, <hi>Father Garnet, Executed at</hi> London <hi>for the Catholick Faith;</hi> that is, for <hi>Treaſon;</hi> which at laſt, it ſeems, is made a part of the <hi>True Proteſtant</hi> Faith alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:63594:11"/>That our King and his Kingdoms are not made a Conſumptive Sacrifice to the Diabolical Fury of theſe <hi>Abaddons,</hi> is a Felicity which we owe onely unto the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwearied</hi> Goodneſs of God to his <hi>Anointed,</hi> and to this <hi>Church;</hi> both which have hitherto been the <hi>Care,</hi> as they both are the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Yet ſtill I ſay, 'tis moſt <hi>unſafe</hi> for us to hug our ſelves with Confidences, if we be not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Husbands of our Time than the <hi>Jews</hi> were; and if we do not ſtudy to doe the <hi>things which belong unto our peace,</hi> while it is yet called <hi>to day.</hi> This I look upon to be the great <hi>end</hi> of our late <hi>Deliverance,</hi> to try whether one Gracious Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation more will work any good upon us. Though it be probable, that as God ſuffered not long ſince a dreadful <hi>Rebellion</hi> to go on, that thereby he might puniſh the <hi>whole Nation;</hi> ſo he may have ſuffered This Horrid <hi>Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> to go on, that thereby he might puniſh the <hi>Traytours themſelves:</hi> yet we muſt not interpret the Providence of God <hi>this way</hi> onely; but we ought to look upon the <hi>Judgment</hi> to have been ſent us to Frighten us all <hi>into</hi> our wits, and upon this <hi>day of Grace</hi> to be given us to this end, that God may make another <hi>Experiment</hi> of us, whether we will yet learn Wiſdom by this one <hi>Miracle</hi> of Mercy <hi>more.</hi> And truly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63594:12"/>
we ſhall build our Hopes upon no other than a <hi>ſhadow,</hi> if we do not found them upon a <hi>Good Conſcience;</hi> and we may <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>latter</hi> our ſelves as we pleaſe; but if we do not heartily ſet about the main buſineſs, and <hi>doe the things which belong unto our peace,</hi> all the mercies of God to us will be utterly <hi>loſt;</hi> and, inſtead of being the <hi>Better,</hi> we ſhall be the <hi>Worſe</hi> for them; and both the Deliverance of <hi>this</hi> day, and all <hi>other</hi> our deliverances <hi>ſince,</hi> will turn to a ſad Reckoning, and greatly <hi>aggravate</hi> our Guilt and Miſery in <hi>the day of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now done with the Explication and Application of thoſe Two Points which are eaſily gathered out of our Saviour's words in my Text. But ſince I am called to this Office, I would not be ſo Rude with this Venerable Auditory, as to omit any thing which may be thought to be either <hi>Proper</hi> for <hi>Me</hi> to add, or <hi>Profitable</hi> for this great Aſſembly to <hi>hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe the Subject I am upon is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of a Practical nature, I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it to be both a fitting and an uſeful courſe for us all, to conſider a little, <hi>what</hi> thoſe things are which at this time of day do very nearly belong unto our peace, and which are apt to <hi>Direct</hi> and <hi>Govern</hi> our Practice rightly, in a matter of ſuch Moment and Importance.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63594:12"/>
For my hopes are, that the Generality of us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being <hi>now</hi> very ſenſible both of our manifold <hi>Dangers</hi> and <hi>Deliverances,</hi> are ſo well diſpos'd to Hearken to thoſe things which really tend to the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi> of our whole <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that 'twill be needful for me but to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound,</hi> and make mention of them <hi>onely.</hi> I muſt therefore beg a little more of your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Patience, while I offer a few things, which if we will but duly obſerve, the Peace we deſire will follow of Courſe, and 'twill be <hi>Impoſſible</hi> for us to be any other than a moſt <hi>Proſperous</hi> and <hi>Happy</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>1. And, firſt, that we may begin at the Right end; it neceſſarily belongeth unto our peace, by conſtant <hi>Prayer,</hi> and ſincere <hi>Repentance,</hi> and by the diligent performance of all offices of <hi>Religion,</hi> and all manner of <hi>Piety,</hi> to make our Peace with Heaven in the <hi>firſt</hi> place. For that on which the whole intereſt of a Nation doth ſolely depend, is <hi>This,</hi> to engage the God of peace on its ſide. Now, as on the one hand, <hi>Irreligion</hi> and hardneſs of heart ſerves to make God an <hi>Enemy,</hi> to ſight <hi>againſt</hi> a Nation (as <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſaid, That the Sins of the <hi>Jews</hi> was that which brought in the <hi>Romans</hi> upon them; and <hi>Titus</hi> himſelf profeſt, That he came againſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63594:13"/>
               <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by a <hi>Divine Impulſe:</hi>) So on the other hand, Mens careful performing of their duty to God, in its ſeveral parts and branches, doth effectually ſerve to make him a <hi>Friend</hi> to fight for a Nation: and <hi>when Mens ways pleaſe the Lord, be maketh even their enemies to be at peace with them,</hi> Prov. 16. 7.</p>
            <p>Here then we are to <hi>Begin;</hi> to make Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Buſineſs and Employment of our Lives. For ſuch is the Horrid <hi>Atheiſm</hi> of our Age, ſuch are the <hi>Profanations</hi> of God's Holy <hi>Name,</hi> and ſo common are all ſorts of <hi>Immorality</hi> and <hi>Debauchery,</hi> that inſtead of wondring at any of our dangers, we may rather wonder that our Calamities are not <hi>Greater</hi> and <hi>More,</hi> and that God's Soul is not yet <hi>avenged</hi> on ſuch a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration as this.</p>
            <p>2. It makes for our Peace, to be <hi>Ingenuous, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright</hi> and <hi>Sincere</hi> in our Profeſſions of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Alas! What Peace can we hope for from <hi>Them,</hi> who make a ſhew of Piety onely to <hi>Cheat</hi> the World, and to ſerve a <hi>Turn?</hi> from <hi>Them,</hi> who go to Churches for <hi>Sanctuary</hi> and <hi>Refuge</hi> onely (as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith the very <hi>Pagans</hi> did when <hi>Rome</hi> was taken by the <hi>Goths</hi> under King <hi>Alaric?</hi>) from <hi>Them,</hi> who uſe Religion as an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrello,</hi> to keep their Treaſons and Villanies
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63594:13"/>
in the <hi>Dark,</hi> and to keep themſelves from the <hi>Heat</hi> of the <hi>Laws?</hi> from <hi>Them,</hi> who are always obſerving the Weather-gage and the <hi>Tide,</hi> and are for ſteering, not the <hi>Beſt,</hi> but the <hi>Safeſt</hi> courſe? from <hi>Them,</hi> that can Temper and Lard their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſo, that you may diſcern for one Layer of <hi>Religion,</hi> many Layers of <hi>Diſhoneſty?</hi> 'Tis all one to theſe, whether there be <hi>Peace,</hi> or <hi>Conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:</hi> Nay, we have ſome Reaſon to miſtruſt, that theſe Men are ready to <hi>Exchange</hi> (I will not ſay Chriſtianity for Turciſm, but) a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Monarch for an Inſidel: I am ſure that they, who have of late been ſo favourable and kind to the <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Intereſt, go upon ſuch <hi>Reaſons</hi> as would make them wiſh the <hi>Turk</hi> the ſame good ſucceſs in <hi>England</hi> (were he at <hi>Our</hi> doors) which they have already wiſht him at the Gates of <hi>Vienna.</hi> It puts me in mind of what was ſaid once by <hi>Cartwright</hi> (that old Zealous Advocate, for a Perfidious and <hi>Turbulent</hi> Sect)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Foulis,</hi> Hiſt. pag. 60.</note> who ſpeaking of complyance with our <hi>Church-rites,</hi> affirm'd, <hi>That we ought rather to conſorm our ſelves in Orders and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies to the Faſhion of the Turks, than to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</hi> There is, it ſeems, ſuch a ſpirit among them, which runs, <hi>ex Traduce,</hi> from the <hi>Father</hi> to the <hi>Child,</hi> that they are willing to admit of a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetan</hi> Habit, rather than a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63594:14"/>
and ſo on, for ought we know, a <hi>Baſſa</hi> rather than a <hi>Lord Mayor,</hi> a <hi>Mufti</hi> rather than a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>a True-Proteſtant Grand Seignior</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince.</p>
            <p>3. Next to our <hi>Religion</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> it greatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth unto our Peace to be very careful of our <hi>Loyalty</hi> to God's <hi>Anointed.</hi> For our Peace being wrapt up in the welfare of the <hi>King,</hi> and in the proſperity of his <hi>Government,</hi> 'tis our <hi>Wiſdoms</hi> to be <hi>True</hi> to <hi>Both;</hi> and 'tis a moſt <hi>Abſurd,</hi> a well as a moſt <hi>wicked</hi> courſe that ſome have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, who would bear us in hand, that to <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce</hi> and <hi>Expoſe</hi> Majeſty, is the way to make <hi>His</hi> Reign, and our <hi>own</hi> Lives <hi>Happy;</hi> and that the <hi>Diminution</hi> of his Prerogatives is the way to <hi>Support</hi> him; and that the deſtruction of his <hi>Life</hi> (another <hi>Curſed</hi> bout at <hi>Lopping</hi>) is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy way to preſerve <hi>Three Kingdoms.</hi> Theſe are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable <hi>Fallacies</hi> put upon the Fickle and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicious <hi>Populace;</hi> and Men are greatly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived if they do not believe, <hi>that every ones In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt is lodged in the King's,</hi> and that the way to make our <hi>ſelves</hi> happy, is, to make <hi>Him</hi> happy in the firſt place. To obey him <hi>Humbly,</hi> to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him <hi>Conſcientiouſly,</hi> and to Love him <hi>Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionately</hi> and <hi>Heartily,</hi> this is at once our Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Duty,</hi> and our Beſt <hi>Intereſt:</hi> whereas, to caſt off that Reverence which he hath a juſt <hi>Right</hi> unto,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63594:14"/>
to <hi>Miſ-conſtrue</hi> his Actions, to <hi>Deprave</hi> his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, to <hi>Suſpect</hi> his Integrity, to <hi>Defame</hi> his Perſon, to render him <hi>cheap, contemptible</hi> and <hi>odious,</hi> and much rather to <hi>Conſpire</hi> againſt his Life (as ſome very <hi>Dainty, Tender-Conſcience-Chriſtians</hi> have done;) This is a <hi>Direct</hi> courſe to tear our <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>All</hi> into pieces, and to lay our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> waſte <hi>without</hi> the help of a <hi>Foreign</hi> Enemy, and though the <hi>Romans</hi> ſit <hi>ſtill,</hi> and ſtir not a <hi>Foot</hi> or a <hi>Finger</hi> againſt us.</p>
            <p>4. Farthermore, it would be much for our Peace, were we but <hi>Candid</hi> and <hi>Kind</hi> in our Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of all our Superiours in Church and State, and not Factiouſly <hi>Suſpicious</hi> of them. For one <hi>Deviliſh</hi> ſtrategem which has been uſed of Late, to bring us firſt to <hi>Confuſion,</hi> and ſo on to <hi>Bloud-ſhed</hi> and <hi>Ruine,</hi> hath been <hi>This,</hi> to Inſinuate to the world, that our Governours are a Cabal of <hi>Conſpiratours</hi> againſt our Religion, and againſt our Laws, and whatſoever elſe is dearer unto us than the skin upon our Hearts. This is manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the deſign of that Cried-up Libel, the <hi>Growth of Popery.</hi> A Treaſonable Pamphlet, concluded to have been written by a <hi>London-Cargillite,</hi> who in the late Helliſh Conſpiracy was a <hi>Common Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatour:</hi> one whoſe Soul and Principles are of the <hi>ſame</hi> Complexion with the <hi>Jeſuites;</hi> and whoſe <hi>Name</hi> conſiſteth of juſt ſo many ſyllables and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63594:15"/>
letters, as <hi>Regicide</hi> and <hi>Maſſacre.</hi> We ſee now for what end <hi>that,</hi> and <hi>other</hi> the like Peſtilent <hi>Libels</hi> were handed about, namely, to doe a piece of Journey-work, firſt for <hi>One Ahitophel,</hi> and then for <hi>Six,</hi> that the King might be deſtroyed, that his Friends might be Butcher'd, and that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment might be Subverted (as They hoped) upon ſome <hi>Colourable Pretences.</hi> Now, if people be thus wickedly perſuaded, that our Governours are unfaithfull to our Religion and Liberties, it cannot be expected that our day of Peace ſhould laſt <hi>long,</hi> but the whole Frame of things in Church and State will be in a <hi>Tottering</hi> condition, and <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> (which have ever been the <hi>Beginning</hi> of our ſorrows) will be ſo ſtrong and epidemical, that at laſt we ſhall inherit the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> whoſe <hi>hand was againſt every man, and every man's hand againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. Again, it would very much conduce to our Peace, if Men were effectually taught to ceaſe from <hi>Reproaching</hi> all ſuch of us, as ſtudy to lead <hi>Quiet</hi> and <hi>Peaceable</hi> Lives in <hi>Godlineſs</hi> and <hi>Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. Herodotus</hi> tells us, that the old <hi>Egyptians</hi> were wont to call all that were not of their own Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Barbarians:</hi> and thence the <hi>Greeks</hi> learnt to call All that were not of their own <hi>Language, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians.</hi> In like manner, 'tis Cuſtomary now
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63594:15"/>
with many raſh and evil men among us, to call <hi>All</hi> that are not of their Faction, <hi>Papiſts;</hi> ſo that let a man be a true Friend to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the <hi>Crown,</hi> and to the Government of the <hi>Church,</hi> and to the <hi>Solemnities</hi> of God's <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and (though he doth all this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuant to thoſe Obligations which are laid upon him by the Precepts of Chriſtianity, and by the Laws of the Land, yet) preſently, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, he is <hi>Branded,</hi> and <hi>Hated,</hi> and <hi>Marked out</hi> againſt another day (among the <hi>Men Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi>) for a <hi>Papiſt.</hi> But I remember, that when <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great was moved to have no Allies but the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and to deal with all other People as <hi>Enemies,</hi> his Anſwer was, that a <hi>Better way would be to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Men and Men by their Vertues, or their Vices, rather than by their Character and Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, becauſe he had found many Evil and Scurvy men among the Greeks themſelves.</hi> And truly it doth become <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> to take the ſame Courſe and Reſolution <hi>now.</hi> Conſidering how abominably <hi>Lewd</hi> and <hi>Vicious, Diſhoneſt</hi> and <hi>Factious</hi> many are that pretend <hi>Religion,</hi> and pretend to be the great <hi>Patriots</hi> of it too, we ſhould do well to take meaſures of men, not by the Length of their <hi>Tongues,</hi> but by the Size of their <hi>Practices</hi> (which will infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63594:16"/>
ſhew what every man is) and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly in taking the tale of our <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Brethren, we ſhould fling <hi>Villains</hi> and <hi>Baſe</hi> Fellows <hi>aſide,</hi> and <hi>diſcount</hi> for them; for if things go on at this rate, and men of the moſt <hi>Callous</hi> and <hi>Brawny</hi> Conſciences be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to paſs and ſhrowd themſelves under the common Name of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> we muſt look upon it to be no other than an <hi>Old Trick,</hi> to Ruin the Kingdom once <hi>again,</hi> and to make <hi>Eighty three</hi> as <hi>Infamous</hi> an Aera as <hi>Forty eight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. There is another thing yet which migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily <hi>belongeth to our Peace,</hi> and 'tis Proper for me to mention it to <hi>You</hi> who are the <hi>Worthy Magiſtrates</hi> of this <hi>Honourable City,</hi> becauſe you are concern'd by your Place and Office to help us to it, and you will be juſtly Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med if you do not <hi>Endeavour</hi> to help us to it, and it is This, that we may be at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> among our ſelves, as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was in King <hi>David</hi>'s time, when ſhe was <hi>moſt Happy. Jeruſalem,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>is built as a City that is Compact toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for thither the Tribes go up, the Tribes of the Lord, unto the Teſtimony of Iſrael, to give thanks to the Name of the Lord. Pſal.</hi> 122. 3, 4. And at the ſixth Verſe he exhorted them to pray for a continuance of <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> Peace,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63594:16"/>
               <hi>O pray for the Peace of Jeruſalem;</hi> as if all its <hi>Proſperity</hi> depended upon that admirable <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Harmony</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in Religion, which was then within its Walls. For nothing doth ſo <hi>Naturally</hi> tend to break the <hi>Peace</hi> firſt of the <hi>Church,</hi> and at laſt of the <hi>State,</hi> as <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Diviſion</hi> doth. It was the very thing which <hi>haſtned Jeruſalems</hi> ruin at laſt, and which was the <hi>direct</hi> Inſtrument of its <hi>Fate,</hi> when its day of Peace was ſpent: So that had not <hi>Titus</hi> ſtruck a ſtroke, the Jews themſelves by their Domeſtick <hi>Feuds</hi> and <hi>Animoſities</hi> would have made utter havock of each other; and the very <hi>Romans</hi> under the Walls, though they were <hi>Enemies,</hi> yet being a People of <hi>Manly</hi> and <hi>Generous</hi> minds, could not but <hi>Pity</hi> the Monſtrous <hi>Follies</hi> of thoſe Miſerable men. And O that <hi>we would know, even we, at leaſt in this our day,</hi> this one thing, which ſo viſibly <hi>belongeth to our Peace!</hi> You cannot but diſcern where the <hi>Seminaries</hi> of <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> do lye, and who are the <hi>Labourers</hi> in them. You cannot but know, that all <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> Aſſemblies are of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a <hi>Breach of the Peace:</hi> And you have reaſon to believe, that People are drawn thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to be taught by degrees how to be <hi>Rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> and <hi>Traytors</hi> under pretence of <hi>Religion.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:63594:17"/>
Is the Nation ready to be on a <hi>Flame?</hi> It is <hi>There</hi> that the Fire it <hi>Kindled.</hi> Is the King and his Government <hi>Beſpattered?</hi> 'Tis <hi>There</hi> that the <hi>Dirt</hi> is gathered up. Are the Laws <hi>Deſied,</hi> and Diſobedience <hi>Pleaded</hi> for? It is <hi>Thence</hi> that Arguments are fetcht. Is the Populace tainted with any <hi>Evil</hi> Principle? It is <hi>Thence</hi> that the <hi>Sowr Leaven</hi> comes. Are any <hi>Seditious</hi> men to be Nominated for a Publick <hi>Office,</hi> or any Friendly Jobb to be done for the <hi>Good Did Cauſe?</hi> 'Tis <hi>There</hi> that Meaſures are taken, and Inſtructions given; and <hi>now</hi> the <hi>Separation</hi> is grounded, not upon point of <hi>Conſcience</hi> to teach men to be <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Honeſt,</hi> but upon point of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy,</hi> to uphold and encourage a <hi>Party</hi> againſt the <hi>Government,</hi> and the <hi>Laws.</hi> 'Tis plain, that as the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian</hi> came into the World much about the ſame <hi>time,</hi> ſo they have been <hi>Kind</hi> to each other like <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> ever ſince, and <hi>both</hi> are Sworn <hi>Enemies</hi> to this <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Church.</hi> You have ſeen enough of their Pranks <hi>already,</hi> and you muſt not expect to ſee <hi>more,</hi> unleſs you will ſtand ſtill and look on, till you ſee your ſelves and the whole Kingdom <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7. To <hi>prevent</hi> which, it is neceſſary for you alſo, by all poſſible means to hinder the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63594:17"/>
Spreading of thoſe <hi>Leud</hi> and <hi>Antimonarchical Doctrines,</hi> which for theſe Five years paſt have made the whole Nation to <hi>Shake:</hi> As, <hi>That the King hath not his Authority imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from God,</hi> (which yet was the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Doctrine) but that the <hi>People</hi> are the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all Authority; that He is Their <hi>Truſtee,</hi> and that they have <hi>Reſerved</hi> to themſelves ſo much of their Power, that they can call a Prince to an <hi>Account,</hi> and <hi>diſpoſe</hi> of his <hi>Crown.</hi> Theſe are Principles, which (to give them that Honour which is due for their <hi>Extraction</hi> and <hi>Kindred</hi>) were firſt <hi>Begotten</hi> by the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit</hi> (the Father of <hi>Ravilliacs</hi>) then <hi>Nurſed</hi> up by <hi>Buchanan</hi> (the Father of <hi>Rebels</hi>) and at laſt <hi>Adopted</hi> by the <hi>Leviathan</hi> (the Father of <hi>Atheiſts.</hi>) And it is impoſſible there ſhould be any <hi>Firm</hi> Peace or <hi>Laſting</hi> Safety, either for <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Subject</hi> in any Kingdom where theſe Doctrines <hi>prevail,</hi> which have been all along <hi>Deſigned</hi> and <hi>Maintained</hi> to <hi>Ruin</hi> Kings, and all Hereditary Monarchies. Theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples made way for the Treaſon of <hi>This Day.</hi> And you may obſerve, that Theſe were the Principles which <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>That</hi> Curſed <hi>Aſſociation</hi> went upon, when they Arraigned and Murthered the <hi>Beſt</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prince that ever was made of <hi>Fleſh</hi> and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63594:18"/>
               <hi>Bloud.</hi> You may read them throughout that <hi>Sad</hi> Trial, and we may be ſure that They who of Late have borrowed of the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> the <hi>Same</hi> Principles, borrowed them for the <hi>Same</hi> Purpoſe; and would have acted upon them ſuch another Tragedy, had not the God of Peace by his Immediate and Special Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence reſcued our Sovereign, and all of us, out of the Claws of thoſe pretending <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> whoſe <hi>Creed</hi> is at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> whoſe <hi>Conſciences</hi> are in their <hi>Cheſts,</hi> whoſe <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Souls</hi> are in the <hi>Field,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Honeſty</hi> is <hi>No where.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Honourable and Beloved, I have humbly offered theſe things to your Conſideration, not only becauſe your <hi>Example</hi> is ſuch as Influenceth the whole Nation, but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your <hi>Loyalty</hi> is ſuch, that you have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a Noble Example to all others, and we doubt not, are ſtill ready to follow after the things <hi>which make for Peace.</hi> That we now Sit every man under his own <hi>Vine,</hi> and under his own <hi>Fig-tree,</hi> is a Bleſſing which we owe, next to the <hi>Providence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> to the <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Excellent</hi> Conduct of thoſe <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>Heroick</hi> Spirits in This City, who have ventured ſo <hi>hardly,</hi> and have waded ſo <hi>reſolutely</hi> through ſo many
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63594:18"/>
Difficulties and Dangers, to <hi>Stop</hi> the Torrent, when a Raging <hi>Inundation</hi> was juſt <hi>breaking in</hi> upon us. This is to your Eternal <hi>Honour,</hi> and God forbid that ever you ſhould be rob'd of any part of it, by taking any Wrong and Unhappy Meaſures, and by Suffering your ſelves to be Supplanted or Over-born by thoſe who <hi>Envy</hi> you the Name of the <hi>Loyal Citizens of London,</hi> the <hi>Reſtorers of our Peace.</hi> For the maintenance of this <hi>Great Character,</hi> no more is needful for you, but to add ſtill to your <hi>Fidelity Diligence,</hi> and <hi>Courage</hi> to your <hi>Wiſdom.</hi> How Crafty are the Children of this World in <hi>Laying</hi> their Deſigns? And how Zealous are they in the <hi>Management</hi> and <hi>Proſecution</hi> of their Intereſt? So it commonly happens, that the <hi>Worſt</hi> Cauſe is <hi>Beſt</hi> Sollica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But as this is <hi>Folly</hi> in our Private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, ſo in Publick Tranfactions it is a <hi>Crime,</hi> eſpecially when the <hi>Life</hi> of a <hi>Prince,</hi> and the very <hi>Being</hi> of a <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity</hi> of a whole <hi>Kingdom,</hi> are all in danger. This I ſpeak the rather, becauſe it has been generally obſerved, that ſome Honeſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, how <hi>Prudently</hi> ſoever <hi>Laid,</hi> have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs <hi>Miſcarried,</hi> and proved <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> for want of <hi>Diligence</hi> and <hi>Care,</hi> and <hi>joynt</hi> Reſolution. In the Name of God let m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63594:19"/>
you to carry a moſt Watchful Eye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe who are <hi>Enemies</hi> to Peace, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring what a <hi>Reproach</hi> was brought upon this Great City by a predominant <hi>Faction</hi> in the <hi>Laſt</hi> Age, which nothing could ever have Attoned for, but the Faithfulneſs and Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of ſome Generous and Right-worthy Citizens in <hi>This</hi> Age. <hi>Your ſelves</hi> have Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, both with <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Indignation,</hi> the Villanies that were acted here at <hi>Common-Halls</hi> and <hi>Common-Councils</hi> in the former times; and I have ſufficient Authority of your <hi>own</hi> to obſerve briefly unto you, ſome of thoſe Horrid Practices which a <hi>Factious</hi> Party then uſed here, Firſt to Deſtroy <hi>one</hi> Prince, and then to Keep out <hi>another.</hi> The Late <hi>Loyal Act</hi> of <hi>Common-Council</hi> hath given us to Underſtand out of the <hi>City-Records,</hi> that 'twas here that a Rebellion was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted in <hi>Forty One:</hi> That here great Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Money and Plate were expended in carrying the Rebellion on in <hi>Forty Two:</hi> That here New Sums and Forces againſt the King were raiſed in <hi>Forty Three:</hi> That here Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts were Puniſht, and their Eſtates taken away in <hi>Forty Four:</hi> That here a Treaſonable Oath and Covenant was Adminiſtred in <hi>Forty Five:</hi> That here a Thankſgiving was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63594:19"/>
for ſeveral Victories over the King in <hi>Forty Six:</hi> That here Reſolutions were taken to ſtand and fall with a Rebellious Houſe of Commons in <hi>Forty Seven:</hi> That here a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition was Voted for Juſtice upon all Capital Actors in the War, from the <hi>Higheſt</hi> to the <hi>Loweſt</hi> (and <hi>but a few Days before the King was Murder'd</hi>) in <hi>Forty Eight:</hi> That here a Petition was drawn for Altering the Laws in <hi>Forty Nine:</hi> That here a Solemn Faſt was held for the good Succeſs of a Rebel-Army in <hi>Fifty:</hi> That here 'twas Reſolved to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture Lives and Eſtates againſt the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> in <hi>Fifty One:</hi> That here a Publick Thankſgiving was Celebrated for the Defeat of the King and his Forces at <hi>Worceſter</hi> in <hi>Fifty Two:</hi> That here <hi>Cromwel</hi> the Uſurper was Careſt and Treated in <hi>Fifty Three:</hi> That here Thanks were given him for his great Care of the Peace in <hi>Fifty Four:</hi> That here Monies were iſſued out for a Diſloyal Militia in <hi>Fifty Five</hi> and <hi>Fifty Six:</hi> That here Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> was Acknowledged in <hi>Fifty Seven:</hi> That here his Death was Condoled, and his Succeſſor Congratulated in <hi>Fifty Eight:</hi> And that here the <hi>Parliament</hi> (ſo called) the Council of <hi>State,</hi> and the Officers of the Army were all Publickly and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63594:20"/>
Splendidly entertained at the Cities Charge in <hi>Fifty Nine.</hi> Such a <hi>Chargeable</hi> and <hi>Coſtly</hi> Rebellion was here for <hi>Eighteen</hi> years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that it is no wonder if your Publick Bank hath been rob'd, not of its <hi>Treaſure</hi> only, but in a manner of the very <hi>Bags.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beloved, I am apt to deal Plainly with All men; and if I deal ſo with You now, it is not with any the leaſt Deſign either to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid</hi> this Honourable <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> or to <hi>Reflect</hi> upon the Memory of your <hi>Loyal</hi> and True-Hearted <hi>Predeceſſors;</hi> but that you may ſee what great Reaſons you have for your Beſt endeavours to follow the things which make for Peace, and to put an Early ſtop to the Growth of a Faction, who when they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their <hi>Duty,</hi> forſake all <hi>Modeſty</hi> and good <hi>Manners,</hi> and by ceaſing to be <hi>Governed</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the moſt Imperious and Heady <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi> the moſt Inſolent and Outragious <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains</hi> in the World. <hi>Every</hi> Good man ought to be very Careful, at leaſt in this <hi>our day,</hi> that he do not Herd or Concur with thoſe Spirits, which but the other day (as it were) to ſhut <hi>out</hi> all <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Power brought it <hi>in,</hi> and to prevent <hi>Popery</hi> laid aſide all <hi>True Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> and the Fear of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:63594:20"/>But this Care eſpecially belongeth unto <hi>You,</hi> the Honourable Governours of this Great Body, and your Timely Zeal for the Intereſt of the King, of the Church and of the whole Nation, will not only be Eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctual to the Eſtabliſhment of ſuch a Peace, as (by the Bleſſing of God) will be tranſmitted to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; but 'twill alſo render your Names <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Precious,</hi> for being the Happy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to Recover the <hi>Ancient</hi> Honour of this <hi>Renowned</hi> City. The Story is well known of <hi>Tylers</hi> Formidable Rebellion, who had the Confidence to ſay (in the Reign of King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second) <hi>that there ſhould be no Law in</hi> England <hi>but what came out of his Mouth.</hi> His Conſpiracy was deſigned to deſtroy the<note place="margin">See <hi>Slow</hi> and <hi>Speed</hi> in <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Nobles,</hi> the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> and the whole Body of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> ſaving the Begging <hi>Friars,</hi> who had no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing to Loſe. That Truly Honourable Perſon, Sir <hi>William Walworth,</hi> was the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> of <hi>London</hi> that year; and that Excellent Man, with the help of ſome of his <hi>Brethren,</hi> ventur'd ſo Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, that the Rebellion failed of Succeſs. For being himſelf in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of danger, he Cryed out, <hi>Ye good Citizens, help your King that is to be Murther'd, and ſuccour Me your Mayor; or if you will not ſuccour Me, yet
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63594:21"/>
leave not your King deſtitute:</hi> This ſo anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Loyal <hi>Citizens,</hi> that in a very ſhort ſpace Sir <hi>William</hi> brought the Traytor's head to the King upon the point of his <hi>Sword.</hi> To Reward this great Service, the King gave <hi>Honours</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> to the Mayor, and his faithful Brethren; and to ſet a particular <hi>Mark</hi> of his Kindneſs upon the whole <hi>City,</hi> and to <hi>perpetuate</hi> the Honour of that day, and the <hi>Memory</hi> of ſuch Signal <hi>Loyalty,</hi> ſome Hiſtorians tell us, that the King order'd the <hi>Sword</hi> to be put in the <hi>Dexter Canton</hi> of the <hi>City-Arms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a Noble Pattern of <hi>Fidelity</hi> and <hi>Fortitude</hi> for every Honeſt Magiſtrate to follow in <hi>Theſe</hi> days; for who is not convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the Truth of a Conſpiracy now? Though, God be Bleſſed, we have not yet the Alarm in our <hi>Streets,</hi> yet we have many <hi>Tylers</hi> that are ready to deſtroy our <hi>Laws,</hi> and to cut our <hi>Throats,</hi> and many <hi>Straws</hi> too (if you will forgive the Expreſſion) that are ready to <hi>Stuff our Skins</hi> alſo; but we have our <hi>Walworths</hi> too; and as our Comfort is, that we are now Bleſs'd with another <hi>Walworth,</hi> ſo our Wiſhes are, that men of ſuch Zeal, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and True Gallantry, may bear the Sword here to the Worlds end.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:63594:21"/>When <hi>Treaſons</hi> are Hatched againſt a moſt Gracious Prince, and the Common Peace is in danger, 'tis Happy that the Sword is in the hands of Such, as will not turn the point of it towards the bowels of that <hi>Authority</hi> which gives it.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Religion</hi> is made the <hi>Viſor</hi> of a <hi>Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 'tis Happy that the Magiſtrate is ſuch, as will not be favourable to thoſe who go to <hi>School</hi> to the <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> and <hi>Truck</hi> with the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf, to make Spoil of the beſt Conſtituted Government in the whole World.</p>
            <p>When this poor diſtreſſed <hi>Church</hi> (the <hi>Envy</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Glory</hi> of all <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi>) is in danger of being torn in pieces by the <hi>Lion</hi> on This hand, and the <hi>Bear</hi> on That, it is Happy for us that the Magiſtrate is ſuch as will think himſelf obliged for <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and for <hi>Gods</hi> ſake, to <hi>Reſcue</hi> the Spouſe of Chriſt from the Jaws of the <hi>One,</hi> and from the Paws of the <hi>Other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And things being thus well provided, it is the part of <hi>every one</hi> of us, to <hi>Study to be Quiet,</hi> and to <hi>do his own Buſineſs,</hi> and ſo in <hi>well-doing</hi> to commit our ſelves into the hands of that good God whoſe Providence careth for us All. It is by means of that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63594:22"/>
               <hi>Good Providence</hi> that we are Aſſembled <hi>this day</hi> to praiſe his Name for our Wonderful Deliverances hitherto, and if we our ſelves be but carefull to Mind the things <hi>which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto our Peace,</hi> we need not doubt but the ſame Providence will deliver us <hi>ſtill,</hi> though <hi>Extremity</hi> of danger ſhould threaten us yet once <hi>again.</hi> For commonly Gods time of ſtepping in between Men and Ruin is then when Dangers are come to that <hi>Hedd</hi> and <hi>Criſis,</hi> that without preſent help from above there is no <hi>Viſible</hi> way of Eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. Thus the Providence of God inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on <hi>This</hi> day, when the <hi>Bloud-thirſty Papiſts</hi> had laid their Deſigns ſo <hi>Cloſely,</hi> ſo <hi>Opportunely,</hi> and ſo <hi>Luckily,</hi> (as They thought) even <hi>beyond</hi> their <hi>Firſt</hi> Hopes, ſo that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſpace of a few hours the Fire was to be Laid, and the King, the Nobles, and the Flower of the whole Nation, were all to be blown up, <hi>Then,</hi> and in that <hi>Nick</hi> and <hi>Critical</hi> Juncture, the Good Providence of God brought to light the hidden Works of Darkneſs, and in the Twinkling of an eye delivered his poor Church, that was juſt <hi>Dropping</hi> into a Chaos.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:63594:22"/>We our Selves have <hi>Lately</hi> ſeen Two ſuch other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of God's Providence; Inſtances, to which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps no <hi>Late</hi> Age, no <hi>Modern</hi> Hiſtory can ſhew us a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel.</hi> The Stupendious Victory in <hi>Germany</hi> over the <hi>Profeſt Enemy</hi> of the Holy <hi>Jeſus,</hi> though Men read it as <hi>News,</hi> yet we may well look upon it as a Signal Inſtance of God's wonderful Providence over ſo many <hi>miſerable</hi> Souls, which were reduced to that condition, that in all Human probability they could not have held out againſt the <hi>next</hi> aſſault. In thoſe their <hi>Laſt</hi> ſtraights, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf made <hi>bare his Holy Arm,</hi> and ſtretch't it out againſt the <hi>Blaſphemous Inſidel,</hi> ſo that almoſt ſuch another over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw was ſeen There, as was in the Camp of the <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Sennacherih,</hi> when there fell an <hi>Hundred Fourſcore and Five Thouſand,</hi> as you read 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>To come nearer <hi>home,</hi> to a Late Miraculous Deliverance wherein we <hi>our Selves</hi> are ſo greatly concern'd: The <hi>Fire</hi> at <hi>Newmarket,</hi> what was it, but one of the moſt <hi>Seaſonable</hi> mercies, that God ever Viſited this Poor Nation with? Had not <hi>Flames</hi> and <hi>Smoak</hi> been imployed to <hi>Drive</hi> the Anointed of God home juſt at that <hi>juncture,</hi> and but a very <hi>little</hi> time before the Inſtruments of Death were plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt him (Lord! I tremble but to <hi>think</hi> of it) the <hi>Breath of our noſtrils</hi> had been ſnatcht away long ago, and Three Kingdoms would have preſently layn weltring in <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Gore.</hi> The very Finger of God was <hi>plainly</hi> ſeen in this; and 'twas the immediate Providence of God that has ſaved us All; <hi>yet ſo, as by Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I have mentioned, not only becauſe 'twas neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for me to take notice of the <hi>Late</hi> miraculous Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>without</hi> which, God knows, we ſhould not have had the Happineſs of meeting together <hi>now,</hi> to Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63594:23"/>
the Deliverance of <hi>this</hi> Day; but alſo becauſe the Conſideration thereof is a very <hi>Proper</hi> and a very <hi>Strong</hi> Argument to Encourage us to depend <hi>ſtill</hi> upon God's good Providence; and eſpecially if we be mindful of the <hi>Main</hi> thing, and Labour to do the things which at this <hi>Critical</hi> time do <hi>belong unto our Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have no more to add, but my hearty <hi>Prayers</hi> to God of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> that as he hath preſerved this Nation from the Ravenage of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Faction hitherto;</hi> ſo he would Preſerve it <hi>ſtill,</hi> and Pardon all our Shameful and Monſtrous Ingratitude: That he would Bleſs our <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign</hi> (that hath all along been as a <hi>Signet upon his right Hand</hi>) with a <hi>Long, Proſperous</hi> and <hi>Peaceable</hi> Reign over us. That he would Bleſs and Support our <hi>Government</hi> which is ſuch a great Bleſſing to Us, that no People under Heaven are ſo Happy as We, if we did but <hi>ſee</hi> and <hi>value</hi> our own Happineſs. That he would Bleſs our <hi>Churhc,</hi> which is under God, our <hi>Safeguard</hi> and <hi>Bullwark</hi> againſt that Foreign Enemy which we are all afraid of. And that he would Bleſs us <hi>all</hi> in turning us all away <hi>from our Iniquities,</hi> and by <hi>opening</hi> our Eyes that we may <hi>ſee the things which belong unto our Peace, before they be hid from us.</hi> All which mercies, God Almighty grant unto us for <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> his ſake, to whom with the <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> be all <hi>Honour, Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Adoration.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:63594:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
